Alexandros Sigaras

Senior Research Associate in Computational Biomedicine

1305 York Avenue Box 140 New York, NY 10021

+1 (646) 962-5634 <u>als2076@med.cornell.edu</u> <u>https://vivo.med.cornell.edu/display/cwid-als2076</u>

Research Interests

My scientific focus is on building secure and Al driven high scalable computing solutions in the cloud for genomic analysis focused on healthcare and more specifically cancer care and cancer research. Furthermore, to visualize these complex big data entities, I am also interested in spatial computing, Mixed Reality, Virtual Reality and Augmented Reality as solutions to enable immersive asynchronous remote collaboration and data visualization of healthcare and genomic data.

Education

December 2013 M.S. in Computer Science, Columbia University, Department of Computer

Science, Fu Foundation School of Engineering and Applied Science, New York,

NY, USA.

Track: Thesis Research Track

GPA: 3.851/4

Thesis: Surgical Structured Light for 3D Minimally Invasive Surgical Imaging

October 2011 B.S. in Computer Science, University of Piraeus, Department of Informatics,

Piraeus, Greece.

Track: Information Systems Track

GPA: 8.5/10

Thesis: Self Adaptive Robotic Warehouse Management Systems with event and

location based triggers

Experience

Weill Cornell Medical College Senior Research Associate in Computational Biomedicine, Institute for Computational Biomedicine, Englander Institute for Precision Medicine

May 2017 -Present

- Lead the design and development of novel software solutions supporting the clinical and research activities at the Joint Clinical Genomics Initiative and at the Englander Institute for Precision Medicine.
- Lead the development of the virtual and augmented reality program for precision medicine:

- Oversee the design, development, and deployment of containerized solutions for the clinical genomics laboratory management system and data analysis, including QC/QA tools
- Lead the efforts of large scale genomic analysis in the cloud for both clinic and research activities; coordinate the development of artificial intelligence solutions to support the precision medicine knowledge base and the case review and sign out process.

Weill Cornell Medical College

Research Associate in Computational Biomedicine, Institute for Computational Biomedicine, Englander Institute for Precision Medicine

April 2015 -May 2017

- Lead the search for new ways to leverage technology to advance precision medicine, including the use of Virtual Reality and Augmented Reality
- Responsible for the design and implementation of the informatics infrastructure of the Englander Institute for Precision Medicine (EIPM), including the design and development of new tools to simplify user interaction with the laboratory information management system and the current IT infrastructure of WCM/NYP, collect and analyze user data and system performance within EIPM, and implement tools to report the results of the genomic analysis to the users via genomic portals.

Weill Cornell Medical College

Programmer Analyst,

Institute for Computational Biomedicine, Englander Institute for Precision Medicine

March 2014 -April 2015

Software Development Lead for all clinical and R&D activities of the Englander institution for Precision Medicine.

Key Responsibilities: Development of Next-Generation sequencing pipelines, LIS, cancer genomic portals and integrating genomic data to New York Presbyterian's HL7 infrastructure.

Columbia University

Research Assistant (graduate), Robotics Lab

September 2012 -March 2014

- Project 1: Developed prototype on Surgical Structured Light for 3D minimally invasive surgical imaging.
- **Project 2:** Developed brain computer interfaces for robotic grasping for people with locked-in syndrome.

Microsoft

Internal Sales Education Specialist

December 2011 -July 2012

Worked closely with universities and K-12 schools in Greece to provide cloud solutions and generally fulfill education institution needs in IT. Recipient of the Language Champion Award for the contribution to the Windows 8 International Review Program.

Microsoft	Microsoft Student Partner
November 2006 - December 2011	Member of Developers Platform Evangelists (DPE) group. Tasks included: administering the departmental Microsoft Developer Network Academic Alliance (MSDNAA) subscription, organizing technical presentations (for students) involving Microsoft products, advising students entering Microsoft's worldwide "Imagine Cup" programming contest, and setting up and moderating the studentguru.gr community website. http://www.studentguru.gr

Honors and Awards

November 2015	Nominee, Forbes 30 under 30 in the Science and Healthcare categories
July 2012	Language Champion Award for Contribution to the Windows 8 International Review Program
June 2012	Fulbright Scholar, U.S Department of State's Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs
June 2012	Scholarship (for M.S. studies), Harry D. Triantafillu Scholarship Fund Award, Institute of International Education
October 2011	Salutatorian, University of Piraeus, Department of Informatics
October 2011	Graduated summa cum laude , University of Piraeus, Department of Informatics
November 2010	Semi-Finalist, Imagine Cup IT Challenge, Microsoft
December 2009	Honorary Scholarship, Hellenic American University
December 2009	2 nd place winner , Athens Startup Weekend 2
November 2008	Semi-Finalist, Imagine Cup IT Challenge, Microsoft

Teaching

Teaching Assistant

- Created and graded homework, midterms, and final exams; prepared project material and gave lectures (Numbers in parentheses indicate enrollment).

COMS W4733 Computational Aspects of Robotics, Columbia University Instructor: Prof. Peter Allen, Fall 2013 (60)

Certifications

December 2011 Udacity - Introduction to Artificial Intelligence - (top 10%)

October 2010 MCP, MCTS - 70-680: Microsoft Technology Specialist – Windows 7,

Configuration

June 2007 MCP, MCTS - 70-680: Microsoft Technology Specialist - Windows Vista,

Configuration

Publications

Journal Articles

- [J.1] Sailer V, Schiffman MH, Kossai M, Cyrta J, Beg S, Sullivan B, Pua BB, Lee KS, Talenfeld AD, Nanus DM, Tagawa ST, Robinson BD, Rao RA, Pauli C, Bareja R, Beltran LS, **Sigaras A**, Eng KW, Elemento O, Sboner A, Rubin MA, Beltran H, Mosquera JM. <u>Bone biopsy protocol for advanced prostate cancer in the era of precision medicine.</u> *Cancer*. 2018 Mar 1;124(5):1008-1015. doi: 10.1002/cncr.31173. Epub 2017 Dec 19.
- [J.2] Pisapia DJ, Salvatore S, Pauli C, Hissong E, Eng K, Prandi D, Sailer VW, Robinson BD, Park K, Cyrta J, Tagawa ST, Kossai M, Fontugne J, Kim R, **Sigaras A**, Rao R, Pancirer D, Faltas B, Bareja R, Molina AM, Nanus DM, Rajappa P, Souweidane MM, Greenfield J, Emde AK, Robine N, Elemento O, Sboner A, Demichelis F, Beltran H, Rubin MA, Mosquera JM. <u>Next-Generation Rapid Autopsies Enable Tumor Evolution Tracking and Generation of Preclinical Models. *JCO Precis Oncol.* 2017;2017. *Epub* 2017 Jun 14.</u>
- [J.3] Bose R, Karthaus WR, Armenia J, Abida W, Iaquinta PJ, Zhang Z, Wongvipat J, Wasmuth EV, Shah N, Sullivan PS, Doran MG, Wang P, Patruno A, Zhao Y, Zheng D, Schultz N, Sawyers CL. <u>ERF mutations reveal a balance of ETS factors controlling prostate oncogenesis.</u> *Nature.* 2017 Jun 29;546(7660):671-675. doi: 10.1038/nature22820. Epub 2017 Jun 14.
- [J.4] Beltran H, Eng K, Mosquera JM, **Sigaras A**, Romanel A, Rennert H, Kossai M, Pauli C, Faltas B, Fontugne J, Park K, Banfelder J, Prandi D, Madhukar N, Zhang T, Padilla J, Greco N, McNary TJ, Herrscher E, Wilkes D, MacDonald TY, Xue H, Vacic V, Emde AK, Oschwald D, Tan AY, Chen Z, Collins C, Gleave ME, Wang Y, Chakravarty D, Schiffman M, Kim R, Campagne F, Robinson BD, Nanus DM, Tagawa ST, Xiang JZ, Smogorzewska A, Demichelis F, Rickman DS, Sboner A, Elemento O, Rubin MA. Whole-Exome Sequencing of Metastatic Cancer and Biomarkers of Treatment Response. JAMA Oncol. 2015 Jul;1(4):466-74. doi: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2015.1313.
- [J.5] Robinson D, Van Allen EM, Wu YM, Schultz N, Lonigro RJ, Mosquera JM, Montgomery B, Taplin ME, Pritchard CC, Attard G, Beltran H, Abida W, Bradley RK, Vinson J, Cao X, Vats P, Kunju LP, Hussain M, Feng FY, Tomlins SA, Cooney KA, Smith DC, Brennan C, Siddiqui J, Mehra R, Chen Y, Rathkopf DE, Morris MJ, Solomon SB, Durack JC, Reuter VE, Gopalan A, Gao J, Loda M, Lis RT, Bowden M, Balk SP, Gaviola G, Sougnez C, Gupta M, Yu EY, Mostaghel EA, Cheng HH, Mulcahy H, True LD, Plymate SR, Dvinge H, Ferraldeschi R, Flohr P, Miranda S, Zafeiriou Z, Tunariu N, Mateo J, Perez-Lopez R, Demichelis F, Robinson BD, Schiffman M, Nanus DM,

Tagawa ST, **Sigaras A**, Eng KW, Elemento O, Sboner A, Heath El, Scher Hl, Pienta KJ, Kantoff P, de Bono JS, Rubin MA, Nelson PS, Garraway LA, Sawyers CL, Chinnaiyan AM. <u>Integrative clinical genomics of advanced prostate cancer.</u> *Cell.* 2015 *May* 21;161(5):1215-1228. *doi:* 10.1016/j.cell.2015.05.001.

Conference Proceedings

[C.1] A Reiter, A Sigaras, D Fowler, PK Allen. <u>Surgical Structured Light for 3D minimally invasive surgical imaging</u>. Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2014), 2014 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on. 2014 November 6, 1282 – 1287. doi: 10.1109/IROS.2014.6942722

Abstracts

- [A.1] J Catalano, G Cheang, D Pancirer, E Merzier, Y Li, H Tran, A Sigaras. 331 The Development of a Custom LIMS: An Introduction and Guide to Successful Implmentation. American Journal of Clinical Pathology, Volume 149, Issue suppl_1, 11 January 2018, Pages S142-S143, doi: 10.1093/ajcp/aqx127.330
- [A.2] H Beltran, K Eng, J Mosquera, A Sigaras, A Romanel, H Rennert, M Kossai, C Pauli, B Faltas, J Fontugne, B Robinson, D Nanus, S Tagawa, J Xiang, F Demichelis, D Rickman, A Sboner, O Elemento and M Rubin. Precision cancer medicine program for whole-exome sequencing of metastatic tumors reveals biomarkers of response. Cancer Research, Volume 75, Issue 15, 1 August 2015, Page 4745 doi: 0.1158/1538-7445.AM2015-4745

Posters

- [P.1] A Sigaras, S Roshal, A Sboner, M Rubin, O Elemento. Healthcare Applications for Immersive Remote Collaboration of 3D Medical Data using Virtual and Mixed Reality. 2017 Startup Symposium, Weill Cornell Medicine, 26 January 2017
- [P.2] E Vinolo, D Alférez, F Amant, D Annibali, J Arribas, M Bentires-Alj, C Bernadó, A Bertotti, A Biankin, A Bruna, E Budinská, A Byrne, C Caldas, O Casanovas, D K. Chang, R B. Clarke, S Corso, G Coukos, V Dangles-Marie, D Decaudin, J Depreeuw, Z Dudová, O Elemento, S Giordano, E Gonzalez-Suarez, H Hafsi, E Hermans, M Hidalgo, G Inghirami, M Jarzabek, S de Jong, J Jonkers, K Kemper, A Křenek, M Kuba, L Lanfrancone, P López Casas, G Mælandsmo, E Marangoni, E Medico, I Miller, K Moran-Jones, B Morancho, F Nematti, J Henrik Norum, H Palmer, D Peeper, P Pelicci, A Piris-Giménez, M Pujana, S Roman, O Rueda, J Seoane, V Serra, A Sigaras, L Soucek, S Tejpar, M Tomas, L Trusolino, A van der Zee, M van de Ven; D Vanhecke, A Villanueva, B Wisman. The EurOPDX Consortium: Objectives, Achievements & Future Directions, 1st EurOPDX Workshop, Switzerland, 3 October 2016
- [P.3] A Reiter, A Sigaras and P Allen. Surgical Structured Light (SSL) for Real-Time Minimally-Invasive 3D Imaging. John Jones Symposium, Columbia University, 10 May 2013

Talks, Lectures

Invited Talks

January 2017 How HoloLens transforms Healthcare

Microsoft Reactor, Grand Central Tech, NY

Host: Microsoft

November 2008 Introduction to Robotics with MS Robotics Studio

Microsoft, Athens, Greece

Host: Microsoft

January 2008 Robotics Warehouse Project

Special presentation to the Chairman of Microsoft, Bill Gates and Konstas Karamanlis, Prime Minister of Greece at the inaugural opening of the Microsoft

Innovation Center in Greece

Host: Microsoft Innovation Center, Greece

December 2007 Introduction to Robotics with MS Robotics Studio and LEGO Mindstorms NXT

IEEE, University of Patras, Greece

Host: Prof. Anthony Tzes

Guest Lectures

December 2015 Precision Medicine

Bioinformatics II, New York City College of Technology, City University of New

York

Instructor: Prof. Evgenia Giannopoulou

November 2011 Intro to Programming in C++ and C#

Introduction to Programming, University of Piraeus, Greece

Instructor: Prof. Ioannis-Christos Panagiotopoulos

December 2010 Introduction to Sketchflow

E-learning, University of Piraeus, Greece

Instructor: Prof. Symeon Retalis

December 2010 Introduction to Expression Blend

Human Computer Interaction, University of Piraeus, Greece

Host: Prof. Maria Virvou

Press and Media Coverage

03/09/2018 Microsoft Developer Blog, Voronoi Selection for Cancer Drug Network Visualization in

Mixed Reality

	drug-network-visualization-mixed-reality/
10/17/2017	Channel 9 , Behind the Scenes: How Weill Cornell Medicine built a chatbot for clinicians to gain fast access to medical data https://channel9.msdn.com/Blogs/DevRadio/DR1747
09/13/2017	Microsoft Windows Blogs, Making mixed reality: a conversation with Alexandros Sigaras and Sophia Roshal https://blogs.windows.com/windowsexperience/2017/09/13/making-mixed-reality-conversation-alexandros-sigaras-sophia-roshal/#B0hV1JuJsZolfG2Q.97
06/15/2017	Microsoft Technical Case Studies, Bot gives Weill Cornell clinicians fast access to medical data https://microsoft.github.io/techcasestudies/bot%20framework/2017/06/15/WeillCornell.html
06/14/2017	Sociable , How Mixed Reality is Transforming Collaborative Cancer Research https://sociable.co/technology/mixed-reality-cancer/
03/26/2017	Arirang, Special Documentary Smart with Heart https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gHa4ddmdCUU
Winter 2016	Weill Cornell Medicine Magazine, Volume 15, Number 3, Virtual Vision – 3D technology could offer a potent weapon in cancer care http://www.weillcornellmedicine/vol_15_no_3?pg=20#pg20
01/27/2016	ABC7 Eyewitness News, New 3D goggles help doctors search for mutations in cancerous tumors http://abc7ny.com/health/new-3d-goggles-help-doctors-search-for-mutations-in-cancerous-tumors/1176716/
07/15/2016	Weill Cornell News, Researchers are Using Virtual Reality to Help Treat Cancer https://weillcornell.org/news/researchers-are-using-virtual-reality-to-help-treat-cancer
07/13/2016	CBS New York, Seen At 11: Doctors Using Virtual Reality To Treat Cancer Patients http://newyork.cbslocal.com/2016/07/13/virtual-reality-cancer-patients/
02/24/2016	Popular Science , Here's How Virtual Reality Could Help Doctors Treat Cancer https://www.popsci.com/how-virtual-reality-could-help-doctors-treat-cancer
05/21/2015	Science Daily, Scientists unveil prostate cancer's 'Rosetta Stone' https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2015/05/150521133732.htm

https://www.microsoft.com/developerblog/2018/03/09/voronoi-selection-cancer-